בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף מ"ז, daf Mem Zayin, we pick
up with the משנה, mishnah, we'll be ending one פרק perek beginning
the next, we pick up with the משנה mishnah at the very
top of מ"ז עמוד א'. Mem Zayin Amud Aleph.
Already a question, you're getting to be like Michael, yeah, go ahead.
Yes, if there's a נזיר Nazir today, could you shave his beard?
Your beard, yes, נזיר Nazir is only about the hair on the
head.
Please shave it. Exactly. The long hair.
Right. מי שנזרק עליו אחד מן הדמים ונטמא. Mi shenizrak alav echad
min hadamim venitma. Okay, so we just have the whole discussion that
according to the
חכמים, Chachamim, even one קרבן korban ends your נזירות, neziroot,
and now we're talking, now one of the, so you've brought one
of the קרבנות korbanot and then you became טמא. tamei. So alright,
what's the problem? רבי אליעזר אומר סותר את הכל. Rabbi Eliezer omer
soter et hakol. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it undoes everything. Now
of course רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you'll remember, is the one who
said you need אחר מעשה כולם, achar ma'aseh kulam, you need all
the קרבנות. korbanot. So that's just a natural, you know, derivation or
like implication of his position.
וחכמים אומרים יביא שאר קרבנותיו ויטהר. Vachachamim omrim yavi shear korbanotav veyit'har.
And the חכמים Chachamim say no, you're done with your נזירות, neziroot,
it doesn't destroy anything, you have an obligation to bring the קרבנות,
korbanot, so you'll bring, so fine, you're done with your נזירות neziroot
and the only thing left is the obligation to bring the rest
of your קרבנות, korbanot, so you do it and then you become
טהור. tahor. Now it's interesting question the order here, it sounds like
you can bring the קרבן korban even before you're טהור tahor and
have your קרבן korban sent to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. As
I mentioned to you, there's a discussion in the גמרא Gemara about
טמא משלח קרבנותיו. tamei meshalayach korbanotav. We actually rule that the only
טמא tamei that can be משלח קרבנותיו meshalayach korbanotav is somebody who
has like a very weak level of טומאה, tumah, somebody who came
in contact with like a שרץ sheretz or a נבילה, neveilah, but
somebody who's טמא מת, tamei meit, or somebody who certainly a, which
is our case here טמא מת, tamei meit, or somebody who's like
a מצורע metzora or זב zav cannot be משלח קרבנותיו. meshalayach korbanotav.
But anyway, that's the הלכה. halacha. But regardless of that, תוספות Tosafot
points out here that certainly we should assume that in the context
of a נזיר Nazir that the תורה Torah does not want you
to be טמא מת tamei meit when you are having your קרבן
korban brought. So like maybe we could have a different discussion if
the נזיר Nazir happened to have been a מצורע, metzora, let's say,
or the נזיר Nazir happened to be a זב. zav. But in
terms of here, it's implicit in the פסוקים psukim that תוספות Tosafot
says that you can't be טמא מת tamei meit when they're being
brought. And he says ויטהר veyit'har actually means,
really means first be נטהר nitehar and then be מביא שאר קרבנותיו.
mevi shear korbanotav. So if you take a look at תוספות: Tosafot:
וחכמים אומרים יביא שאר קרבנותיו ויטהר, Vachachamim omrim yavi shear korbanotav veyit'har,
פירוש לכשיטהר. peirush lichsheyit'har. When you become טהור, tahor, then you may
bring it. כך מפרש בירושלמי סתם מתניתא דטהרה ואחר כך יביא קרבנותיו.
Kach mefaresh biyerushalmi stam matnita d'tahara v'achar kach yavi korbanotav. Now why
does תוספות, Tosafot, what do we know that, ומנא לן? uminalan? והרי
אותו הזבח שהיה בהכשר לא יחזור ויביא. Va'harei oto hazevach shehayah be'hechsher
lo yachzor veyavi. You don't have to re-bring that one. רבנן דמאי
דמי אחר מעשה יחידי מותר לשתות יין ולגלח. Rabbanan d'mai dami achar
ma'aseh yechidi mutar lishtot yayin u'legale'ach. So alright, so fine, you were
done with your נזירות, neziroot, you were, the טומאה tumah did not
destroy anything, the קרבן korban was
good. הרי הוא קודם שנטמא ראוי לתגלחת. Harei hu kodem shenitma ra'uy
litiglachas. So למה
יסתרנו? lamah yisterenu? אבל הזבחים שהקריב משנטמא יסתור. Aval hazevachim shehikriv mishenitma
yistor. Anything he brought afterwards before he became טהור tahor is not
good. How do we know that? So you could say a general
rule of whether a טמא tamei can have his קרבן korban brought,
but again, who knows what that general rule is. But here specifically,
דקפיד קרא שיביא קרבנות נזירות בטהרה. dekapid kra sheyavi korbanot neziroot betaharah.
ואחר שנטהר ויהיה לו הזיה ג' וז' יביאם. Ve'achar shenit'har veyiheyeh lo
hazayah gimmel v'zayin yavi'em. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says because if you
read the פסוקים, psukim, right, the פסוקים psukim say if he becomes
טמא, tamei, we discussed this before, he goes through a process of
טהרה taharah and then has the קרבן korban brought. So there's a
sense in which the טומאה tumah is a סתירה. stirah. We actually
discussed that, you know, earlier. We said that on day seven he
becomes טהור tahor and day eight he brings the קרבן. korban. You
know, so the תורה Torah sort of seems to really want to
not have a נזיר טמא Nazir tamei have his קרבן korban of
נזירות neziroot brought. Now you could have said that that's when the
טומאה tumah is a סתירה stirah to the נזירות. neziroot. Now that
the טומאה tumah is no longer a סתירה stirah to the נזירות,
neziroot, essentially is, right, that's when he became טמא מת tamei meit
and he could not continue his נזירות neziroot in that status and
so on. You could say the תורה Torah wanted him to be
totally טהור, tahor, right, and he had to bring his קרבן korban
like a נזירות דטומאה neziroot d'tumah on day eight after he has
become totally טהור tahor from טומאת מת. tumath meit. Here where he's
no longer a forbidden in טומאה, tumah, his נזירות neziroot is effectively
over, it's not so clear that he can't be a טמא מת
tamei meit and have the קרבן korban brought. But תוספות Tosafot seems
to be still tapping into that model, implicit model that we saw
when a נזיר Nazir becomes טמא מת. tamei meit. The תורה Torah
wants him fully out of that before any קרבנות korbanot are being
brought. But again, you could make it specifically about נזיר וטומאת מת,
Nazir v'tumath meit, or you could make it a general question about
whether somebody who is טמא tamei can have the קרבן korban brought.
Either way though, it's those points are not clear in the משנה.
mishnah. The משנה mishnah says bring the קרבן korban and then be
טהור. tahor. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi reads it, bring the קרבנות korbanot once
you become טהור, tahor, right? So it's a whole question anyway how
to read that line in the משנה. mishnah. The other point to
make about this משנה, mishnah, and surely I will get back to,
the other point to make about this משנה mishnah is that when
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says סותר את הכל, soter et hakol, how
obvious does it literally mean סותר את הכל? soter et hakol? You
might remember... Remember that there was an earlier רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* that actually said that it only סותר *soter* seven days
when it's after the full thirty days. So סותרת הכל *soteret hakol*
itself might not really mean סותרת הכל *soteret hakol*. Take a look
at תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot*, he says it's the first תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*:
ונתמא רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer, סותר הכל ולא V'lo כל
Kol הימים כמפורש בגמרא דרבי אליעזר הוא דאמר לעיל נטמא לאחר מלו
סותר זין אלא Ela סותר קרבנות קמא *V'nitma Rabi Eliezer omer soter
hakol v'lo kol hayamim k'mforesh ba'Gemara d'Rabi Eliezer hu d'amar l'eil nitma
l'achar milo soter zayin ela soter korbanot kama*. And that's important, right?
Because here, and that is true, that is the context of the
משניות *Mishnayot*. The context of the משניות *Mishnayot* is, like yesterday when
we talked about you shaved and you realized you had shaved, you
know, when the first קרבן Korban *korban* wasn't good, that the קרבנות
*korbanot* that you brought afterwards are no good. So the context here
is whether the קרבנות *korbanot* that come afterwards remain good or not.
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer... *Rabbi Eliezer* would say you became טמא
Tamei, *tamei* and you were not done with your נזירות Nezirut, *nezirut*,
any קרבנות *korbanot* after would also be no good, and the קרבן
korban, *korban* you brought before also will be no good, whereas the
חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* say no, the קרבן korban, *korban* you brought before
is good, the טומאה Tumah, *tumah* does not undermine the נזירות Nezirut.
*nezirut* in any way, and after you become טהור tahor, *tahor* you
can finish bringing the rest of the קרבנות *korbanot*. So the focus
here is not the days but the קרבנות *korbanot*, but obviously there's
a relationship between those two. Finish the משנה mishna *Mishna* and then
get back to the question that there was, and then it says
like this: אמרו לו Amru lo, *Amru lo*,
so the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim* said to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* that מעשה במרים התרמודית *ma'aseh b'Miriam haTarmodit*, there was a story
with מרים *Miriam* from תרמוד *Tarmod*, שנזרק עליה אחד מן הדמים *shenizrak
aleha echad min hadamim*, one of the קרבנות *korbanot* were brought, ובאו
ואמרו לה על בתה שהייתה מסוכנת *uva'u v'amru lah al bittah shehayta
mesukana*, and then they told her that her daughter was in danger,
she had, I don't know, she had fallen down a well or
something, והלכה ומצאה שמתה *vehalcha u'matza shemeta*, when she ran to save
her daughter and she found that her daughter had died, ואמרו חכמים
Chachamim *v'amru Chachamim*, so then she became טמא מת Tamei Meit, *t'mei
met* after one קרבן korban. *korban* was brought and she was a
נזירה *nezira*, תביא שאר קרבנותיה ותטהר *tavi shear korbanoteha v'tit-har*. Okay, so
it's very sad that her daughter has died, as far as the
נזירות Nezirut *nezirut* is concerned,
her נזירות Nezirut *nezirut* was done after one קרבן korban *korban*, so
now she does the, that קרבן *korban* was not undermined, was not
destroyed, and let her become טהור tahor *tahor*, let her bring the
rest of her קרבנות *korbanot*. She still has an obligation of the
קרבנות *korbanot*, let her bring them after she becomes טהור tahor. *tahor*.
Yes, Charlie, you had a question.
Regarding the issue of bringing, having someone bring a קרבן *korban* for
you when you
on your behalf when you're טמא Tamei *tamei*, yeah,
טמא Tamei, *tamei* or or about to become not טמא Tamei *tamei*.
Are there some קרבנות *korbanot* that can be brought for you like
the קרבן פסח *korban pesach*?
קרבן פסח *korban pesach* actually is the one
that cannot be brought is the most restrictive that can't be brought
for you when you're טמא Tamei *tamei*. There is a question about
somebody who's a טבול יום *tevul yom* and will be, yeah, that's
a different story. He'll be able to eat the קרבן פסח *korban
pesach* that night, but the קרבן פסח *korban pesach* is brought for
him during the day and he can eat it that night.
But do you have to have already gone to the מקוה *mikvah*
before they can bring it for you?
Yeah, pretty positive, yes. Okay. Yeah, let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Yeah. In the same animals that they to they became טהור tahor.
*tahor*, they already had the animals when they purified themselves for seven
days.
Yeah, they would be, if those animals have been sanctified, they remain
sanctified, yeah, and then they would be brought when the time comes.
I have to ask this
though, yeah, where is תרמוד *Tarmod*? I have no idea.
Oh, it's Palmyra.
I knew you would tell us.
In Syria?
In Syria. Some weird shape of the ruins that were there before
Islamic State destroyed them.
Okay.
So that's a place where they,
ah, right there, that's it. That's where what? That's the place that
ISIS destroyed in order to wipe any archaeological evidence of pagan pre-monotheistic
Islam. Wow.
Not only that, they murdered the archaeologist who was the caretaker.
Oh my god. Oh my god. Two tissues?
On another note.
No, sorry, but they are in the back, I guess.
All right. קתני *Katani*: רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר סותר את הכל
*Rabbi
Eliezer omer soter et hakol*, ואמר רבי אליעזר כל Kol אחר מלאות
Melot? שבעה סותר *v'amar Rabbi Eliezer kol achar milot shiva soter*, so
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* already sort of anticipated or whatever told us ahead
of time this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. What do you mean it destroys
all after the full thirty days, טומאה Tumah *tumah* only makes you
do another seven days according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. אמר רב
מאי סותר דקאמר רבי אליעזר סותר קרבנותיו *Amar Rav mai soter d'ka'amar
Rabbi Eliezer soter korbanotav*. It destroys the קרבנות *korbanot*, so any קרבנות
*korbanot* that you had done you have to redo now because your
נזירות nezirut, *nezirut* is no longer over, and any קרבן *korban* you'll
do after until you finish your נזירות nezirut, *nezirut* are no good.
הכא נמי Nami סברת דחכמים אם תביא שאר קרבנותיה ותטהר *Hacha nami
savarta d'chachamim im tavi shear korbanoteha v'tit-har*. שמע מינה *Shma mina*, שמע
מינה *shma mina*. So we're talking about the question about the קרבן
*korban*, not about the number of days. But the and the חכמים
*Chachamim* are saying that the first קרבן *korban* is so good. ומעשה
נמי במרים התרמודית שנזרק עליה אחד מן הדמים ובאו והודיעוה על בתה
שהייתה מסוכנת והלכה ומצאה שמתה ואמרו חכמים תביא שאר קרבנותיה ותטהר *U'ma'aseh
nami b'Miriam haTarmodit shenizrak aleha echad min hadamim u'va'u v'hodi'uha al bittah
shehayta mesukana v'halcha u'matza shemeta v'amru chachamim tavi shear korbanoteha v'tit-har*. שמע
מינה *Shma mina*. So you see the whole question here is about
the קרבנות *korbanot*, it is not about the question about the number
of days, obviously they're dependent because if it destroys the נזירות nezirut,
*nezirut* then you need more days, your קרבנות *korbanot* are not good,
but the focus is on the קרבנות *korbanot*. הדרן עלך
שלושה מינים *Hadran alach sheloshah minim*. which ended by some of the
rituals of ending the נזירות nezirut and what process and what exact
things end the נזירות, one קרבן or all the rituals etc, but
the focus of it were on the איסורים Issurim of the נזיר,
Nazir, of shaving the hair, drinking wine, and coming טמא, Tamei which
is very important because it introduces us to three areas of הלכה
Halacha that are more generally relevant. From the issue about the wine,
we got into all discussion about, no, about what do you call
it? About טעם כעיקר Ta'am Ke'ikar and about taste that of non-kosher
things that occur in a mixture and when, you know, it's still
able to be tasted. Regarding the issue of shaving the hair, we
discussed the issue about shaving the beard and shaving the sidelocks and
what defines shaving in other areas. And regarding the issue of טומאה,
Tumah we began a discussion about טומאת כהנים Tumat Kohanim about number
one, if a כהן Kohen or a נזיר Nazir is already טמא
Tamei. מת, Met do they transgress again when they become טמא Tamei,
again? And the issue of מת מצוה. Meit Mitzvah. And now actually
in this coming פרק, Perek, we are going to continue to focus
on the issue of טומאה Tumah because there is much more to
be learned from the relationship of נזיר Nazir and כהן Kohen regarding
the restrictions of the כהן. Kohen. And just to anticipate besides that
we're going to once again look at מת מצוה, Meit Mitzvah, but
the other thing that really that you have to know is the
principle which is called כל טומאה שאין הנזיר מגלח עליה אין כהן
מוזהר עליה. Kol Tumah she'ein haNazir Megale'ach aleha ein Kohen muzhar ala.
So, or אין הנזיר מגלח עליה ein haNazir Megale'ach aleha I guess,
anyway, so any טומאה Tumah that a נזיר Nazir would not shave
for, okay, a כהן Kohen is not prohibited against. Now it does
not just mean טומאת שרץ Tumat Sheretz or טומאת נבלה Tumat Neveilah
or זב Zav or מצורע, Metzora, that would be obvious. It means
that even within the realm of טומאת מת, Tumat Meit, there are
some things that cause טומאת מת Tumat Meit that nevertheless we have
a קבלה Kabbalah for, a נזיר Nazir it does not would not
have to shave and would not have to restart his נזירות. And
also that applies therefore equally to a כהן. Kohen. So one of
the interesting areas that we're going to be looking at are things
that are actual טומאת מת Tumat Meit and nevertheless are somehow excluded
from the prohibitions of טומאת כהנים Tumat Kohanim and from the implications
for the נזיר Nazir that he would restart his נזירות if he
came in contact with them. Okay, so there's still yet a lot
to be seen to be explored in terms of the issue of
טומאה tumah with נזיר Nazir and particularly with relevance even for contemporary
issues regarding כהנים. Kohanim. So let's take a look now at the
next פרק. Perek.
What is ימלאו Yimal'u mean and כל הימים לא שבעה סותר? kol
hayamim lo shiva soter?
That after the full thirty days, if you become טמא, Tamei it
only you only have to redo seven days, not the full thirty.
So the thirty days is מלאות? It's after the thirty. Okay, thanks.
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, yes.
You take relating the נזיר Nazir to the כהן, Kohen, and does
that negate the idea of נזירות as a sin to become a
נזיר? Nazir? Because the כהן Kohen is like the ultimate holy person.
Yeah well look, I mean, it's true, you know, in the simple
sense of the פסוקים, Pesukim, the idea that there's something sinful about
being a נזיר Nazir is not פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Pesukim
I would sort of I would agree with that. You know, the
sense is is that it's like a self-accepted upon status that is
similar not only to a כהן Kohen but even to some degree
to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. You don't even become טמא Tamei
to immediate relatives. You know, though please a little quieter.
So but yeah, but I mean it's something that the גמרא Gemara
raises, but I don't think that you get the hint about that
in the תורה Torah that aspect. Okay, but whether or not, you
know,
anyway, right, it certainly is a sense is a level of קדושה
Kedusha that you have. Nobody says being a נזיר Nazir does not
put you at a certain level of קדושה. Kedusha. The question is
is whether self-imposing that is a good idea or not. But once
you're there, you know, that certainly is true about your status. Okay,
so let's take a look. So the first thing before we get
though to the question about the again the restrictions and what might
technically be excluded because of the type of טומאה tumah. that we're
dealing with even within טומאת מת, Tumat Meit, we once again look
at the issue about מת מצוה. Meit Mitzvah. So let's take a
look. כהן גדול ונזיר, Kohen Gadol veNazir, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and a נזיר, Nazir, אין מטמאים לקרוביהם, ein mitam'im likroveihem, they cannot
become טמא Tamei to their relatives, so in that way a נזיר
Nazir is similar to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Right? A כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, and this is interesting, right, meaning a normal כהן
Kohen becomes טמא Tamei to his relatives. A כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
basically the idea is is conceptually he's always supposed to be in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Not that he always is, but like
conceptually מן המקדש לא יצא. min haMikdash lo yeitzei. Completely supposed to
be sort of there standing ready to represent the people to God,
in God's presence, you know, and therefore never can take himself away
from that function, you know, even for immediate relatives. It always gets
to that question, right, about like, you know, important public people, often
men or whatever, that are like not there for their family because
they're too much doing this important public role. And then there's always
that question, right? So it's interesting, you know, in terms of the
תורה Torah like okay, one guy, like maybe there's that the one
גדול הדור, Gadol HaDor, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that like okay,
he ignores his family and he's always in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Everybody else like, you know, when your family something else with
your family, you're leaving the you're leaving the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
you become טמא. Tamei, So the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol though is
the one person... who stays in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or
whatever, doesn't leave his role, doesn't become טמא, Tamei, which would, wherever
he physically is, you know, would take him out of that role
when he even when an immediate relative dies. Interestingly, the נזיר, Nazir,
now you would think a guy wants to become a נזיר, Nazir,
maybe that puts him at the status of similar to a כהן,
Kohen, right? I mean, doesn't become... but no, but actually in the
פסוקים, Pesukim, it actually is similar to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
in that way. He doesn't even become טמא Tamei to immediate relatives.
Okay, so כהן גדול ונזיר אין מיטמאין לקרוביהן, Kohen Gadol v'Nazir ein
mitamim likroveihen, they do not become טמא Tamei. even to their immediate
family, אבל מיטמאין למת מצווה, aval mitamim lemeit mitzvah, they do become
טמא Tamei. to a מת מצווה, meit mitzvah, and this is again
not in the פסוקים, Pesukim, but what the rabbis understand. היו מהלכין
בדרך, Hayu mehalchim baderech, they were going on the way, ומצאו מת
מצווה, u-matzu meit mitzvah, and they found a מת מצווה. meit mitzvah.
So which one should become טמא Tamei first? Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר,
יטמא כהן גדול ואל יטמא נזיר, yitma Kohen Gadol v'al yitma Nazir,
let the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol become טמא, Tamei not the נזיר.
Nazir. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, יטמא נזיר ואל יטמא כהן גדול, yitma
Nazir v'al yitma Kohen Gadol, no, let the נזיר Nazir one and
not the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And actually it argues, it says
יטמא כהן הדיוט, yitma Kohen Hedyot, but then it says יטמא כהן
גדול. yitma Kohen Gadol. They might... וחכמים v'Chachamim might say one, we'll
see. וחכמים v'Chachamim might say that it's even if it's just between
a נזיר Nazir and a normal כהן, Kohen, which would explain the
גרסה girsa of הדיוט. Hedyot. Even if it's not between a נזיר
Nazir and כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, even a נזיר Nazir and a
normal כהן, Kohen, more and more the normal כהן's Kohen קדושה kedusha
has to be more protected than the נזיר's. Nazir So let's see
why. Let's see why. אמר להם רבי אליעזר, Amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer,
Rabbi Eliezer said to them, יטמא כהן שאינו מביא קרבן על טומאתו
ואל יטמא נזיר שמביא קרבן על טומאתו. yitma Kohen she'eino meivi korban
al tumato v'al yitma Nazir shemeivi korban al tumato. No, the נזיר's
Nazir טומאה tumah, has to be more protected. The נזיר, Nazir, where
if he actually becomes טמא, Tamei it destroys his נזירות, he brings
a קרבן, it's more consequential. I mean, for both of them under
normal circumstances it's a לאו. lav. But here it's permitted because there's
a מת מצווה. meit mitzvah. Right, now this shows you to some
degree, I mean this is a question let's say when פיקוח נפש
pikuach nefesh overrides שבת, Shabbos, when מת מצווה meit mitzvah overrides טומאה.
tumah, One of the ways to conceptualize that question is הותרה hutra
or דחויה. dichuya. How much do you sort of see like the
prohibition still apply, but this is a more important thing and therefore
it overrides. But if the prohibition still apply, you want to minimize
the amount of transgression or you want to... nobody's transgressing, but you
want to minimize the amount of overrides that are necessary. Or do
you basically say like הותרה, hutra, in these circumstances it's like there's
no such thing as טומאה, tuma like these prohibitions don't exist at
all. So this sort of reflects this more of this דחויה dichuya
idea, right? We're going to try to sort of protect as much
as possible. It's necessary to be ניתמא nitma to take care of
this מת מצווה meit mitzvah and you shouldn't hesitate, like nobody's going
to say, you know, and you don't do the types of things
that might slow it down or get in the way. But if
you can make a sort of a spot decision and minimize the
amount of override, we try to do that. So which one, how
do we most protect the things that need to be most protected?
So רבי אליעזר is saying, look clearly the נזיר Nazir being טמא
Tamei is a bigger consequence than the כהן. Kohen. Under normal circumstances
they'd both be a negative prohibition. Okay, but there's something much more
weightier about the נזיר Nazir becoming טמא. Tamei He has to restart
his נזירות, he has to bring a קרבן, so it's much more
consequential. So clearly that's the thing that makes more sense to protect
and let's let the כהן, Kohen, even a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
become טמא. tamei That makes more sense.
And what about נזיר שמשון? Nazir Shimshon? Then they don't bring a
קרבן. Why? Because נזיר שמשון מיטמא למתים Nazir Shimshon mitamei lemeitim to
begin with.
Oh, that's true. Okay, well then obviously נזיר Nazir wouldn't even be
a question. Okay, so that's what he says. It's more consequential, so
we protect the נזיר Nazir more.
רבי אליעזר... אמרו לו, they said back to him, no, יטמא נזיר
שאין קדושתו קדושת עולם. yitma Nazir she'ein kedushato kedushat olam. Let a
נזיר Nazir become טמא tamei because that's only a temporary status. So
yes, on the one hand in practice it undoes it and you
have to bring a קרבן and so on. But on the other
hand, this is not so much about his permanent... about his identity,
right? It's a temporary status that he has. So that sense that
his, you know, when a כהן Kohen you say his... the קדושת
כהן kedushas Kohen has been violated, that's central to his identity and
who he is. There's a greater violation that's occurring there to that
קדושה kedusha than a נזיר Nazir that's a temporary status.
ואל יטמא כהן שקדושתו קדושת עולם, v'al yitma Kohen shekedushato kedushat olam,
and not a כהן, Kohen, which is why the earlier גרסה girsa
said that they might say look, רבי אליעזר says I'd rather a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol become טמא tamei than a normal נזיר. Nazir.
And the חכמים are saying we'd rather a נזיר Nazir become טמא
tamei. than even a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, right? Because if it's
about קדושת עולם, kedushat olam, it could even be כהן הדיוט. Kohen
Hedyot. So that might be why when it gets to the חכמים,
this גרסה girsa switches to הדיוט. Hedyot. So for רבי אליעזר even
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol becomes טמא tamei. before a נזיר, Nazir,
and for חכמים even a נזיר Nazir becomes טמא tamei, even before
a כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. Now what about if he's a נזיר
עולם? Nazir Olam? If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot. like
the second wide line here, נזיר קדושתו קדושת שעה ואפילו אמר נזיר
עולם מכל מקום סתם נזירות הרי שלושים יום. Nazir kedushato kedushat sha'ah
v'afillu amar Nazir Olam mikol makom stam nezirut harei shloshim yom.
So תוספות Tosafot says even if in this case the guy is
a נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, the concept of נזירות, the nature of
קדושת נזירות kedushat nezirut is interesting because maybe there's a different quality
to the קדושה kedusha of נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, but the concept
of נזירות is for thirty days. quality of נזירות *nezirut* is fundamentally
something that is not about identity, it's about a status that's accepted,
it's not necessarily a permanent identity, a natural one, you know, and
so on, it could be shaped by the person, he chose to
make it permanent, so it does not have that same sort of
weight as the status of a of the קדושת כהונה *kedushat kehuna*,
the violation there is greater, which is interesting because how do you
measure the violation, right? I mean רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says let's
look at הלכתית *halachikly* the fallout, the חכמים *Chachamim* even though there's
no really fallout of the violation of the קדושת כהונה *kedushat kehuna*,
they still say nevertheless it's a greater violation. דוב *Dov* you had
a question?
Yeah, is that just a special הלכה *halacha* לגבי כהנים *legabei kohanim*
that if they become טמאים *tme'im* they don't bring a קרבן *korban*
as opposed to anybody else?
Not a special הלכה *halacha*, nobody comes טמא tamei, *tamei* if they
become... nobody brings a קרבן *korban* if they... well no, no, not
nobody. For טומאת מת tumat meit *tumat meit*, meaning there are some
types of טומאות tumos, *tumot* that a קרבן *korban* is the process
of טהרה tahara *taharah*. For example, the טומאה tuma, *tumah* that יוצא
מגופו *yotzei migufo*, זב zav, *zav* and a זבה *zavah* and מצורע
metzora *metzorah* etc. But of course, we're talking about for the violation,
we're talking about טומאת מת tumat meit. *tumat meit*, which is the
only prohibition for כהנים *kohanim* is טומאת מת tumat meit *tumat meit*,
the other things are not the... are not what the כהנים *kohanim*
are proscribed against, the כהנים *kohanim* only proscribed against טומאת מת tumat
meit. *tumat meit*, and טומאת מת tumat meit. *tumat meit* the... the
process of becoming טהור Tahor. *tahor* doesn't involve a קרבן *korban*, and
the violation doesn't require a קרבן *korban*. For a נזיר Nazir? *Nazir*
the violation of the נזירות *nezirut* requires a קרבן *korban*, not the
טהרה *taharah* process. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
בשלמא כהן גדול kohen gadol ונזיר *Bishlama kohen gadol venazir*, היי סבר
*hai savar* we understand what the debate is about between those two,
between... where it's between the two of them. היי סבר כהן גדול
kohen gadol עדיף והיי סבר נזיר nazir, עדיף *Hai savar kohen gadol
adif vehai savar Nazir adif*. Okay, they spelled out their reasons in
the משנה mishna *mishna* very nicely. So we understand that. Now we're
going to ask a couple of thought questions about other people that
we might have to choose between who becomes טמא tamei. *tamei* first.
Okay? What if it's משוח בשמן המשחה ומרובה בבגדים *Mashuach beshemen hamishcha
u'merubeh bivgadim*? You have two כהן kohen גדולים *kohen gedolim*. One כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol. *kohen gadol* has been anointed with the anointing oil,
which was sort of נגנז *nignaz* and lost to us in the
time of King יאשיהו *Yoshiyahu*, and the other becoming... was a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol. *kohen gadol* afterwards by just having worn the שמונה
בגדים Begadim *shmoneh begadim*. So they're both כהן kohen. גדולים *kohen gedolim*
and they're both walking down the street. Now of course the question
is one minute, how are they both living at the same time?
You can't answer time machine, that's not a fair answer. Anyway, so
it could be, okay, this was the generation when the שמן המשחה
*shemen hamishcha* got lost was... was... was secreted away towards the end
of the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash*, okay, so then
the next... but what happened to the first כהן גדול Kohen gadol.
*kohen gadol* who was משוח בשמן המשחה *mashuach beshemen hamishcha*? So all
right, well maybe he had been... תוספות Tosafot? *Tosfot* sort of tries
to figure this out. Maybe he had been... been a בעל קרי
*ba'al keri* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* and you needed
to substitute with another כהן kohen *kohen* and there wasn't any שמן
המשחה *shemen hamishcha* at that stage, so the other guy was מרובה
בבגדים *merubeh bivgadim*. But that makes one of them an active כהן
kohen *kohen* and the other guy a previously having served כהן kohen
*kohen*, which is going to be like the next question the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s going to ask. So I will... so תוספות Tosafot *Tosfot*
tries to figure out how you have this scenario that they're both...
you have both at the same time in history and you don't
have it like one is active and the other is a past
כהן kohen *kohen*. Let's bracket that, I'll try to get back and
tell you how תוספות Tosafot *Tosfot* explains how it could happen. But
for now let's ignore... let's not... let's just imagine that theoretically you
had them both and they were both either equally active or equally
retired and you had a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *kohen gadol* who
was משוח בשמן המשחה *mashuach beshemen hamishcha* and one who's מרובה בבגדים
*merubeh bivgadim*. Which one comes first? So it seems that's like an
easy question. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says משוח בשמן המשחה עדיף *mashuach
beshemen hamishcha adif* or what... which one do you protect their... you
know, do you protect more, does not become טמא tamei, *tamei*?
So the one who was anointed with the oil is better, דאילו
משוח בשמן המשחה מביא פר על כל המצוות *de'illu mashuach beshemen hamishcha
meivi par al kol hamitzvot* because there's a special הלכה *halacha* which
is the same way when the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* rules incorrectly and most
of כל ישראל yisrael *Klal Yisrael* follow them, they bring a special
קרבן *korban* in מסכת הוריות Horayos. *Masechet Horayot* a פר העלם דבר
של ציבור *par helam davar shel tzibur*. If a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, *kohen gadol* rules incorrectly and actually follows his own ruling... this
is actually a very interesting הלכה *halacha*. It needs a הוראה *hora'ah*
and a following of the הוראה *hora'ah* but all personal. Okay, so
not just he sinned, then he'd bring a normal קרבן *korban*. Not
just he פסק *paskened* and other people listened to him, then there
wouldn't be a קרבן *korban*. He פסק *paskened* and he followed his
own פסק *psak*, okay, in that case there's... what? Exactly. In that
case
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *kohen gadol* brings a special קרבן *korban*.
But that is only brought, the תורה Torah *Torah* describes it as...
as the one who is נמשח *nimshach*, I forget the לשון *lashon*
of the פסוק posuk *pasuk*. But anyway, משמן המשחה *meshemen hamishcha*... whatever...
whatever the פסוק posuk *pasuk* is there, okay, it describes it specifically
as the כהן kohen. *kohen* that is... that is נמשח בשמן המשחה
*nimshach beshemen hamishcha*. So משוח בשמן המשחה עדיף, דאילו משוח בשמן המשחה
מביא פר על כל המצוות, ואילו מרובה בגדים Begadim אין מביא *mashuach
beshemen hamishcha adif, de'illu mashuach beshemen hamishcha meivi par al kol hamitzvot,
ve'illu merubeh begadim ein meivi*. Okay, so therefore there is one way
in which this one has a higher status than the מרובה בבגדים
*merubeh bivgadim* and that's why clearly his קדושה *kedusha* would be seen
as higher and you would protect it more. Okay. So that's that
הלכה *halachah*. Now, we'll go through all of this and then I'll
deal with some of the issues that תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* questions that
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* raises about this. Let's say you have the following
case: משיח שעבר ומרובה בגדים Begadim *Mashuach she'avar u'merubeh begadim*. Now this
is an easier one to imagine. You have a guy who was
משיח בשמן המשחה *Mashuach Beshemen HaMishcha*, but he is he has past.
He is no longer in active service. Why? So now you could
say he served in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and
then he became טמא tamei, *tamei* and now he's you know and
then they they appointed another one and the other one they didn't
have the שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha*, he was מרובה בגדים Begadim, *merubeh
begadim*. The only problem is is that after the one who became
טמא tamei, *tamei* becomes טהור Tahor *tahor*, he gets back into service
and the guy who served once he becomes sort of permanently off
duty. So how do you get what? Put out to pasture. Put
out to pasture. So the question is how do you get the
one who was משיח בשמן המשחה *Mashuach Beshemen HaMishcha* which logically chronologically
comes first because first you had the שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha* before
you did it, but have him to be the one that is
put out to pasture? Since, right you get it if the guy
was כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* first and then number two
had a substitute for him then when when number one comes back
and number two is the guy they put out to pasture. How
do you get that the one that chronologically came first to be
the one that was put out to pasture? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*
has the scenario let me see if I can remember how תוספות'ס
*Tosfos's* scenario hold on which was
what's תוספות'ס *Tosfos's* scenario?
Oh I can't even remember. Okay you know what let's go through
the גמרא *Gemara* and then I'll try to go back and figure
out how תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* figures out how all this works. Okay
let's take a look. So anyway you have somehow though that case
that the guy who has this higher level of anointing of of
becoming the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol* nevertheless is the guy
that's like on permanent off duty and you have the one who
is מרובה בגדים *merubeh begadim*. So in that case מרובה בגדים עדיף
*merubeh begadim adif* דמרובה בגדים *de'merubeh begadim* עביד עבודה *avid avodah*. No
there even though what's more weighty than this issue about משיח בשמן
המשחה *Mashuach Beshemen HaMishcha* is the fact that practically you are on
active duty and the guy on active duty his קדושה *kedushah* is
higher and therefore has to be protected more or not only higher
but you know it would more the טומאה tuma. *tumah* would more
interfere with him being able to do his עבודה *avodah*, so he
is the one who is protected and the משיח בשמן המשחה *Mashuach
Beshemen HaMishcha* is the one who will become טמא Tamei *tamei*. Now
ואילו משיח שעבר *ve'ilu Mashuach she'avar* לאו בר עבודה הוא *lav bar
avodah hu*. He's not somebody that can any way he's been permanently
put on off duty so he can no longer do the עבודה
*avodah*. He clearly will be the one who will become טמא Tamei
*tamei*. Now עבר מחמת קריו ועבר מחמת מומא *avar machmas kiryo ve'avar
machmas muma*. Let's say both of them are now currently off duty
but one you have two כהנים *Kohanim* who are off duty two
כהנים גדולים *Kohanim Gedolim* who are off duty. One is off duty
because he was a בעל קרי *ba'al keri* he had a seminal
emission and the other because he had a blemish on his body.
So עבר מחמת קריו עדיף *avar machmas kiryo adif*. So the one
who was put off duty because of his seminal emission is more
important that means he's more protected does not become טמא Tamei *tamei*.
דהוא חזי לעבודה למחר *de'hu chazi le'avodah lemachar* because he'll just go
to the מקווה *mikveh* and be able to serve tomorrow. ואילו עבר
מחמת מומא *ve'ilu avar machmas muma* and the one that's been put
off duty because of a blemish לא Lo חזי לעבודה *lo chazi
le'avodah* and תוספות *Tosfos* says even if it's a temporary blemish you
don't know when it will heal as opposed to the guy who
became טמא Tamei *tamei* because of a בעל קרי *ba'al keri* it's
just a one day problem. Okay so clearly that's the one you're
going to protect more. So all of those are obvious. Okay how
exactly you get some of those scenarios are not obvious but all
of those preferences priorities are
obvious. Here איבעיא להו *iba'ya lehu*. Now here's the question that we
want to raise. That we get. Here is the question we want
to raise. איבעיא להו *iba'ya lehu*. משיח מלחמה וסגן *Mashuach milchamah ve'sgan*
היי מניהו עדיף *hai minaihu adif*. Let's say you have one guy
who's anointed and both of these are like one level lower than
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*. These are like executive vice presidents.
Okay so one is the guy who's anointed to lead the people
into war right the כהן kohen, *Kohen* comes and he says מי
האיש הירא ורך הלבב ילך וישוב לביתו *mi ha'ish hayarei ve'rach halevav
yelech ve'yashuv leveiso* etc. and he has a spe- he has a
really a high level he has a specially anointed for that role
and you have another guy who is the vice כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol *Kohen Gadol* and he is the guy that's there so in
case the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol* becomes טמא Tamei? *tamei*
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* in particular when you really
need a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol? *Kohen Gadol* because יום כיפור Yom
Kippur? *Yom Kippur* is the only time you really need a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* that this guy steps in in his
place. Okay so which one and they both there bump into a
dead body. So היי מניהו עדיף *hai minaihu adif*. Which one is
is on a higher level that you protect them? משיח מלחמה עדיף
*Mashuach milchamah adif* דחזי למלחמה *de'chazi le'milchamah* because he's like has a
very special role. He's the guy that has the ability to lead
the people in the war. That's a very high and special status
and you want to protect that. או דילמא סגן sgan. עדיף *o
dilma sgan adif* or maybe the סגן sgan. כהן kohen. *sgan Kohen*
is better is more important דחזי לעבודה *de'chazi le'avodah* because he's fit
to do the עבודה *avodah* and particularly like the עבודה *avodah* of
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* the עבודה *avodah* in the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol*
gets becomes טמא tamei *tamei* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*.
So תא שמע Ta Shma *ta shema* that's an interesting question right
one is somehow an objective higher status like you would think look
the guy who's the active משיח מלחמה *Mashuach milchamah* clearly right now
has a very weighty role the סגן sgan, *sgan*... סגן sgan? is
just like the vice president. You know, the vice president's job is
to wait for the president to die, right? So like, I mean,
who's more important, right? The Secretary of Defense or the vice president?
Most of the time it's the Secretary of Defense. The only time
the vice president matters is the president's about to die. So that's
the question, right? So you might think you want to protect the
משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama more, okay? So because that's a more important
status. Of course the interesting question is that a משוח מלחמה mashuach
milchama one imagines probably comes טמא tamei on a pretty regular basis
when he is doing his job. He's out there in the battlefield.
One wonders where he is when the actual action actually starts, but
okay. Anyway, so let's take a look. תא שמע דתניא: tashma detanya:
אין בין משוח מלחמה לסגן אלא שאם היו מהלכים בדרך ומצאו מת
מצוה יטמא משוח מלחמה ואל יטמא סגן. ein bein mashuach milchama lesgan
ela sheim hayu mahalchim baderech umatz'u meis mitzvah yitamei mashuach milchama ve'al
yitamei sgan. No difference between the two of them except the following:
if they're going on the way and they found a מת מצוה,
meis mitzvah, יטמא yitamei משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama ואל יטמא סגן. ve'al
yitamei sgan. The משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama becomes טמא tamei and not
the סגן. sgan Okay, now, why would you say that is, right?
Given that the משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama most of the time is
playing a much more important role than the סגן, sgan why do
you think the משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama becomes טמא tamei before the
סגן?
sgan
How often do you have a war?
Well, let's even backeting that. Let's say you will...
can you think why? Because the whole purpose of the סגן sgan,
is to be ready if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol becomes טמא.
tamei His whole job description is stay ready. Don't be טמא. tamei
Stay ready because we're going to need you if the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol. becomes טמא, tamei right? So he is the... his primary
responsibility is to make sure that he is טהור, that he's always
ready to step in. So even if in general the משוח מלחמה
mashuach milchama is an active service and playing a more active role,
you know, he's not just in the sort of in the wings
waiting to come on stage, he actually is on stage, but the
סגן's sgan, primary responsibility is to be טהור so that he'll be
ready to step in. So he actually cannot become טמא, tamei you
let the משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama become טמא.
tamei I would say your point, I think to me more strongly,
the סגן sgan is actively staying טהור. In other words, he's actively
his job the same way that the... Okay, right.
Okay, you can say it that way. You can say it that
way. And even if by the משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama becoming טמא,
tamei you need to get another משוח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, you know,
you need to appoint somebody else. But fine, okay, so yeah, there
will be a consequence, but at least that's not a fundamental violation
of his prime responsibility as a משוח מלחמה. mashuach milchama. It's true
if I'm משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama and I become טמא, tamei they're
going to need to find somebody else. Fine, let 'em find somebody
else, but that my basic responsibility was not to preserve my טהרה
status. As opposed to the סגן, sgan he was basically there supposed
to be keeping at the ready. Okay, so that seems to be
the idea. ואל יטמא ve'al yitamei סגן. Sgan והתניא, vehatanya, but don't
we teach in a ברייתא? braisa? משוח מלחמה קודם לסגן, mashuach milchama
kodem lesgan, that משוח מלחמה mashuach milchama comes before the סגן, Sgan
has a higher priority? So אמר רב זוטרא, amar Rav Zutra, fine,
לענין החייתו משוח מלחמה עדיף. le'inyan hachayoso mashuach milchama adif.
That's from that whole ברייתא, braisa, that whole discussion in הוריות. Horayos
People might know that there's a משנה mishna, in הוריות that tells
who comes before whom. And that basically is the question like the
משנה mishna about triage, like if you have to save somebody's life.
Very challenging משנה, mishna like, you know, are you really supposed to
make choices about saving somebody's life because this person's a כהן kohen.
and this person's a ישראל or whatever. Very important תשובה teshuvah that
רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein does, which he pretty much makes
that משנה mishna almost completely moot, which רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein says, he says that
משנה mishna which gives a list of prioritizing of whose life do
you save first is only if every single other factor imaginable in
the universe has already been taken into consideration. Like, you know, how
bad is their injury, and what's, you know, you know, all, you
know, what's the likelihood that they'll survive, but you've taken in every
single factor you could imagine at in the entire universe to determine
who should come first in terms of triage and it all exactly
is even, then you look at this as the very last thing
to determine. That's how רב משה Rav Moshe reads that משנה of
who comes first, okay? Which pretty much makes it completely moot. But
anyway, but that's a משנה that speaks about those priorities. So then
the question is, so ah, so don't you see? So the גמרא
says that's true. When there's a question that they're both down a
well and I gotta save one of them or something of that
nature and I could only save one, so לענין החייתו משוח מלחמה
עדיף. le'inyan hachayoso mashuach milchama adif. מאי טעמא דתלי ביה רבים? mai
ta'ama detali beih rabim? It's like, you know, if I gotta save
the Secretary of Defense or the vice president, I'm going to save
the Secretary of Defense. Right now he's doing a much more important
job and he's doing a job that everybody is, you know, protecting
the the security of the people. So obviously, you know, playing a
role in in or at least playing a role in that. So
obviously his job is more important at this stage and he has
to be saved first. What if there's one job that has to
be saved right now, it's his. Or one person because of their
job. ולענין טומאה סגן עדיף. ule'inyan tumah sgan adif. But when it
comes to טומאה, tumah? then we have to protect the סגן Sgan
more, דתניא detanya רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר למה תיקנו סגן לכהן
גדול שאם יארע בו פסול הרי נכנס ומשמש תחתיו, Rebbi Chanina Ben
Antigonus omer lama tiknu sgan lekohen gadol she'im ye'arei bo psul harei
nichnas umeshamesh tachtav, 'cause the whole job of the סגן Sgan is
to remain טהור. So when it comes to not becoming טמא, tamei
that's the primary responsibility. So
that's basically this interesting גמרא about like how you would sort of
queue certain types of priorities. Let's read to the end of the
דף daf and then we'll go back and try to unpack some
of the scenarios we might have before. Oh, but you know what
before we do I do want to say one thing about the
סגן Sgan. and the משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama because the ברייתא Braisa
said אין בין סגן למשוח מלחמה. Ein bein Sgan l'Meshuaich Milchama. This
is the only difference. You know, is it about choosing between who
becomes טמא tamei and then it threw in or who do you
save if you have to save one of their lives? Okay. But
תוספות says what do you mean? I mean there's tons of differences.
The משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama is almost like a quasi כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol Take a look at תוספות. Okay. תוספות says like this:
תא שמע ודתניא Vedatanya אין בין משוח מלחמה, Ein bein Meshuaich Milchama,
you see that תוספות? About eight lines down in the wide lines.
לסגן L'sgan אלא שהיו She-hayu מהלכין Mehalchin בדרך Baderech ומצאו U'matzu מת
מצווה Mes Mitzvah יטמא Yitamei משוח מלחמה. Meshuaich Milchama. וקשיא V'kashya טובא.
Tuva. תוספות says it's very difficult. איכא Ika בינייהו. Beinaihu. וקשיא, V'kashya,
excuse me, טובא Tuva איכא Ika בינייהו. Beinaihu. There's a lot of
things that are between them. כי הא Ki ha דבסוף D'vesof יומא
Yoma בגדים שכהן גדול She-kohen gadol משמש Meshamesh משוח מלחמה Meshuaich milchama
משמש. Meshamesh. The משוח מלחמה Meshuaich milchama wears the בגדים of the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol והסגן V'hasgan עובד Oved בבגדי B'vigdei הדיוט Hedyot
כמו Kmo שעובד She-oved ביום הכיפורים B'yom hakippurim נמי תחת Tachat כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol That's an interesting insight. The סגן Sgan while he's
in his סגן Sgan role, you have before and even if he
hasn't substituted yet for the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol wears normally the
בגדים of a כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. Now I would just say
because in his סגן Sgan role he hasn't yet been filling the
place of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol but תוספות also makes an
interesting insight. His whole job is to substitute for the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur Well, the role of the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is to wear
he wears the normal בגדים, the בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan. Okay. ותו
V'tu תוספות says כל חמישה Chamisha דברים Devarim האמורים Ha-amurim בפרשה B'parsha
לא פורע Porea ולא פורם Porem ועל V'al כל נפשות Nafshot מת
Mes, יבוא Yavo ועל V'al בתולה Betulah ואסור V'asur באלמנה B'almanah דאינן
De-ainan נוהגין Noigin בסגן B'sgan ונוהגין V'noigin במשוח מלחמה. B'meshuaich milchama. All
the restrictions of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol? He can only marry
a בתולה, Betulah, you know he can't rend his garments if there's
a מת, you know he can't marry an אלמנה, Almanah, all those
things only apply to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the משוח
מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama not to the סגן. Sgan's The משוח מלחמה Meshuaich
Milchama was effectively a quasi כהן גדול kohen gadol in a different
sphere. Not in the בית המקדש but out in the battlefield. So
תוספות what do you mean אין בין? Ein bein? So תוספות says
the אין בין Ein bein means אין בין Ein bein to be
give more weight to the where there's no difference there's never a
time where we give more weight to the סגן Sgan except to
protect him when they find a מת מצווה. Mes Mitzvah. There's plenty
of times we give more weight to the משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama
but there's never a time when we give more weight to the
סגן Sgan except except that he doesn't become טמא tamei if it's
between him and the and the and the משוח מלחמה. Meshuaich Milchama.
Okay. So first of all just that you should be aware, you
would have left the גמרא with the impression that a סגן Sgan
and משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama are effectively the same and actually it's
not true. A משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama is really like a quasi
כהן גדול. kohen gadol Okay. But nevertheless what it's saying and that's
why also you save him first, he definitely actively is playing a
much more important role. But nevertheless when it becomes with a מת
מצווה Mes Mitzvah the סגן's Sgan job is to stay טהור. So
in that case the משוח מלחמה Meshuaich Milchama becomes טמא tamei first.
Yes. סגן sgan only appointed in terms of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur.
In terms of filling in for the כהן גדול? kohen gadol You
mean would he you mean you mean would he only have been
appointed on ערב יום כיפור? Erev Yom Kippur? Or would he take
the position of the כהן גדול kohen gadol only if the כהן
גדול kohen gadol became טמא tamei during יום כיפור Yom Kippur period
or any time during the year? No it seems like only יום
כיפור Yom Kippur? like there's no really other time of the year
where you really need a כהן גדול. kohen gadol Why else they
discuss him that like when did it occur? Yeah, I mean or
did it occur within like or did it occur like more than
a week before יום כיפור Yom Kippur? or something like that? Right,
right, right, right. Yeah, it's a good point. Like I mean presumably
since it's talking about סגן it mean I was assuming like it
meant in the context where סגן was relevant, but you're right. I
mean that could have been raised like who's even like what time
of year we talking about? Yeah. He wasn't appointed at least a
week before יום כיפור. I know I know but they discuss as
like why don't we just say that if it was like a
month before יום כיפור then let the סגן become טמא? tamei Or
do we somehow see this as part of his role and even
when it's not immediately relevant, nevertheless it's still is like part of
his like, you know, identity right now? You know I don't know,
it's a good question. It's a good question. Would the same thing
be true a month before יום כיפור? Yeah. סגן כהן גדול Sgan
Kohen Gadol is referenced a lot in ש"ס. Shas. Right, but his
responsibilities, like, that's I think David's question. Like, in terms of his
status, I mean, you know, his responsibilities of making sure he becomes
טהור and so on, you know, how much is that specifically, you
know, relating to what do you call it, specifically relating to יום
כיפור? Look, the point is is that while you didn't strictly need
a כהן גדול kohen gadol, the rest of the time, right, you
still wanted, you know, the I mean, you know, I have to
I have to look into it a little bit more to be
honest because it might be true you don't need a but the
בית המקדש can function without a כהן kohen. גדול. Is it at
all times or is it specific? That's what you're asking, right? You
might strictly be able to get by without a כהן kohen, גדול
the rest of the year, but nevertheless do we see the סגן's
responsibility to be year-round, right? To be there to fill in? It's
a very good question. I have to I have to look into
that. Okay, so now let's take a look. The גמרא says like
this: עד כאן לא פליגי אלא בכהן גדול ונזיר. Ad kan lo
peligi ela be-Kohen Gadol ve-Nazir. So until now the whole question is
who do you become טמא tamei first, a כהן kohen, גדול or
a נזיר? nazir Who do you want to protect more? כי קא
אזלי בהדי הדדי Ki ka azli bahadi hadadi if they're going at
the same time. אבל חד חד לחודיה בר צמויי אינון Aval chad
chad le-chudei bartzit meiyei inun but each one individually we take for
granted that they override their restrictions in order to become טמא tamei
for מת מצוה. met mitzvah. So מנא הני מילי Minani milei where
do you get this from? How do you know that? I mean
the תורה Torah never says a מת מצוה met mitzvah takes precedence.
So the גמרא says דתנו רבנן detanu rabbanan we taught and we've
quoted a little bit about this earlier: על כל נפשות מת לא
יבוא, Al kol nafshot met lo yavo, right, this is what it
says by the כהן. kohen ולאביו ולאמו לא יטמא U-le-aviv u-le-imo lo
yitama ומנא מיקש שלא יצא וכולי u-mina mikash shelo yetzei ve-chulei etc.
Okay, so על כל נפשות מת לא יבוא, al kol nafshot met
lo yavo, don't enter into any place where there's a dead body.
במאי קרא מדבר Bemai kera medaber who's it talking about? אי ברחוקים
I bi-rechokim if it's about non-relatives so why do you have to
tell me a כהן kohen גדול can't become טמא tamei to non-relatives?
קל וחומר הוא, Kal va-chomer hu, you can make a קל וחומר
kal va-chomer from a כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. ומה כהן הדיוט U-mah
Kohen Hedyot a normal כהן kohen שמטמא לקרובים אין מטמא לרחוקים she-mitamei
li-krovim ein mitamei li-rechokim who is טמא tamei to relatives cannot become
טמא tamei to non-relatives, כהן גדול שאינו מטמא לקרובים Kohen Gadol she-eino
mitamei li-krovim כהן kohen גדול we're going to find out that it
says ולאביו ולאמו לא יטמא le-aviv u-le-imo lo yitama can't become טמא
tamei to relatives אינו דין שאינו מטמא לרחוקים? eino din she-eino mitamei
li-rechokim? How much more so that if he can't become טמא tamei
to relatives how much more so can he not become טמא tamei
to non-relatives? So why did the תורה have to tell me על
כל נפשות מת לא יבוא? al kol nafshot met lo yavo? Of
course he can't become טמא tamei to a normal dead person. אלא
בקרובים הכתוב מדבר Ella bi-krovim ha-katuv medaber it must be talking when
it says על כל נפשות מת al kol nafshot met it must
mean he can't become טמא tamei even to relatives. So if על
כל נפשות מת al kol nafshot met must mean relatives because it
would be redundant to say that על כל נפשות מת al kol
nafshot met meant non-relatives, right? That's obvious, a normal כהן can't be
טמא tamei to relatives, non-relatives, how much more so a כהן גדול
can't become טמא tamei to non-relatives. So that's true, על כל נפשות
מת al kol nafshot met must be referring to relatives. If על
כל נפשות מת לא יבוא al kol nafshot met lo yavo means
relatives then why did it have to go back and say ולאביו
ולאמו לא יטמא? le-aviv u-le-imo lo yitama? That now becomes redundant. So
if that's true אלא בקרובים ולאביו הוא דאינו מטמא. ella bi-krovim u-le-aviv
hu de-eino mitamei. Now the word ולאביו le-aviv is extra. I already
know you can't become טמא tamei to relatives and nevertheless it says
don't become טמא tamei to the father. הא מטמא הוא למת מצוה
Ha mitamei hu le-met mitzvah that's sort of like a מיעוט אחר
מיעוט אלא לרבות. miyah achar miyah ela lerabbot. You've already said don't
become טמא tamei to relatives, that's על כל נפשות מת, al kol
nafshot met, so by saying now don't become טמא tamei to the
father it's telling you but there is somebody you can become טמא
tamei to, מת מצוה. met mitzvah. Now there's a little circularity here
which is that the whole קל וחומר kal va-chomer that we know,
what's the קל וחומר? kal va-chomer? A normal כהן can become טמא
tamei to his father and can't become טמא tamei to non-relatives, so
a כהן גדול who can't become טמא tamei, to his father of
course he can't become טמא tamei to non-relatives either. But one minute,
how do we know a כהן גדול can't become טמא tamei to
relatives? How do we know he can't become טמא tamei to relatives,
a כהן גדול? Because it says ולאביו ולאמו לא יטמא, le-aviv u-le-imo
lo yitama, right? So we use that, right, you understand, right? Okay,
so he
writes it: על כל נפשות מת לא יבוא ולאביו
ולאמו לא יטמא.
Al kol nafshot met lo yavo le-aviv
u-le-imo lo yitama.
So we want to know who the על כל נפשות מת al
kol nafshot met are. So we say that that means relatives. And
that since that means relatives ולאביו le-aviv is extra and that means
but yes, a מת מצוה, met mitzvah, right, that's what we say
because we've already decided that this means relatives. Now how do we
know this means relatives? Because they say look at the קל וחומר.
kal va-chomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal va-chomer? A normal כהן can
become טמא tamei to his father and can't become טמא tamei to
non-relatives. So a כהן גדול who can't become טמא tamei to his
father of course he can't become טמא tamei to non-relatives also. So
you wouldn't have to tell me non-relatives, so this must mean relatives,
okay? But the only way we know that this means relatives is
because we already said ולאביו le-aviv literally is necessary to tell you
he can't become טמא tamei to his father, right? So it's like
a little bit circular, how can we now say ולאביו le-aviv is
extra? The only way we were able to say to make a
קל וחומר kal va-chomer started on the fact that we knew that
he couldn't become טמא tamei to relatives. So תוספות basically says it's
not really a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, the קל וחומר kal va-chomer
is really like a little circular, really it's a more simple point.
The simpler point is a כהן גדול is no less than a
normal כהן. So a כהן גדול is already prohibited to become טמא
tamei against becoming טמא tamei to non-relatives just in his role as
a normal כהן, just in his status as a normal כהן. Okay?
So that's really the point. This כהן גדול already is restricted against
becoming טמא tamei to non-relatives. He's a כהן.
He's a כהן.
So why does it have to say this? This can't be telling
you non-relatives, of course he's already restricted to non-relatives. So this must
be God telling you don't become טמא tamei even to relatives. Once
it's telling you that, then the rest of the פסוק is extra,
okay? So it's really not a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's really
more since he's a normal כהן, of course he's already restricted against
non-relatives. So this therefore must be relatives, which makes לאביו ולאמו laviv
uleimo extra to allow us to make a דרשה. drasha. Okay? So
that's one דרשה drasha that make מצווה. mitzvah. Now let's just see
what it does with לאמו uleimo and we'll end with that.
ולאמו, uleimo, he says, is גזירה שווה gezeira shava לדרבי. liderabi. דתניא,
detanya, it says in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
גבי נזיר
במותם... gabi nazir bemotam... גבי
נזיר במותם אינו מטמא אבל מטמא הוא לניגעם ולזיבתם. gabi nazir bemotam
eino mitamei aval mitamei hu lenigam ulezivatam. It says by a נזיר,
nazir, לא יטמא להם במותם, lo yitama lahem bemotam, in their deaths.
So a נזיר nazir. cannot become טמא tamei to people who are
dead, but he can become people that have other טומאות, tumos, like
they are a מצורע metzora or they're a זב, zav? they have
a flow. והא מיעטא בנזיר veha miyata benazir because it emphasizes במותם,
bemotam, okay, only the טומאה tumah of death is an issue. Okay,
בכהן גדול מנלן, bekohen gadol minalan, how do I know a כהן
גדול is allowed to have other טומאות, tumos, come in contact with
people that are מצורע or
זב? מנלן, minalan, אמרת לא יאמר אמו amarta lo yomar imo בכהן
גדול, bekohen gadol, it didn't have to say אמו. imo. שהרי שאין
תלמוד לומר שהרי קל וחומר הוא. sheharei she’ein talmud lomar sheharei kal
vachomer hu. You could already make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, similar
type of a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה במקום שכהן הדיוט מטמא
לאחיו
מאביו, uma bemakom shekohen hedyot mitamei leachiv me’aviv, אין כהן גדול מטמא
לאביו. ein kohen gadol mitamei le’aviv.
Okay, so this is a even more complicated קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
but really the same point. But here's the basic point.
The point okay... let's... well okay let me read it through. ומה
במקום שכהן הדיוט מטמא לאחיו מאביו, uma bemakom shekohen hedyot mitamei leachiv
me’aviv, a normal כהן, a כהן הדיוט, kohen hedyot, can become טמא
tamei to his brother on his father's side, and nevertheless, אין כהן
גדול מטמא לאביו, ein kohen gadol mitamei le’aviv, and a כהן גדול
can't even become טמא tamei to his
father. Okay? מקום שאין כהן הדיוט מטמא, makom she’ein kohen hedyot mitamei,
a place where a normal כהן cannot become טמא, tamei who is
that? לאחיו מאמו, leachiv me’imo, a half-brother on his mother's side, because
we're obviously in a patriarchal system, it's not really the family if
it's only on the mother's side. So what does that show you?
Here's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. A normal כהן becomes טמא tamei
to a brother on the father's side, not on the mother's side,
which basically shows you that what? That father weighs more than mother.
Father's family weighs more than mother's family, because even a normal כהן
who becomes טמא to relatives, it's only relatives on the father's side,
not relatives on the mother's side. So if that's true, and you
already know that a כהן גדול can't become טמא to a father,
then how much more so he can't become טמא to a mother?
So why did it have to say mother?
So אם זכיתו מן הדין מה תלמוד לומר אמו? im zachito min
hadin mah talmud lomar imo? And if you could make it by
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, why did it have to say אמו?
imo? Another way of saying that is, if this פסוק על כל
נפשות מת al kol nafshos meis already means relatives, why do you
have to say mother? Once this first part means relatives, both of
these are extra. Okay, the way this ברייתא braisa is saying it
is if אביו, aviv, if you can't become your father, certainly you
can't become טמא to your mother. Or you could say, if you
can't become טמא to all relatives, both אביו aviv and אמו imo
are extra. So what is mother teaching you?
מה תלמוד לומר אמו mah talmud lomar imo בכהן גדול? bekohen gadol?
מופנה, mufneh, it's open, להקיש ולדון ממנו גזירה שווה lehakish veladun mimenu
gezeira shava to connect it and to make a גזירה שווה. gezeira
shava. נאמר אמו בנזיר ונאמר אמו בכהן גדול. ne’emar imo benazir vene’emar
imo bekohen gadol. It says אמו imo by both of those. מה
אמו האמור בנזיר במותם אינו מטמא אבל מטמא הוא לניגעם ולזיבתם, mah
imo ha’amur benazir bemotam eino mitamei aval mitamei hu lenigam ulezivatam, the
same way by a נזיר, nazir it says במותם, bemotam, he's only
restricted against becoming טמא for dead bodies, not for other types of
טומאה, tumah. אף אמו האמור בכהן גדול במותם אינו מטמא אבל מטמא
הוא לניגעם ולזיבתם. af imo ha’amur bekohen gadol bemotam eino mitamei aval
mitamei hu lenigam ulezivatam. But he can become טמא for people, כהן
גדול, for other טומאות, tumos טומאות of צרעת tzaraas and of זיבה
zivah and other types of טומאה. tumah So it's...
yeah, אמו imo connects to the אמו imo of נזיר. nazir, By
a נזיר nazir it
says
לאביו
ולאמו ולאחיו ולאחותו לא יטמא להם.
le’aviv ule’imo ule’achiv ule’achoso lo yitama
lahem. להם lahem במותם. bemotam. Okay, so במותם bemotam tells you only
טומאת מת tumat meit is the problem, okay? That's what you know
by a נזיר, nazir only טומאת tumat מת. Okay. Here, you don't
know, it says don't become טמא to your mother and father. What
made me all טומאה? tumah. How do you know it means only
only their dead bodies, right? I mean על נפשות מת al nafshot
meit is their dead bodies, but לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא, l'aviv ul'imo
lo yitama, maybe any טומאה tumah my mother and father has I
can't become טמא to them, okay? So לאמו l'imo connects you to
the לאמו l'imo of the נזיר and it says, so לאביו l'aviv
tells you you're allowed to become טמא to a מת מצווה, meit
mitzvah, okay? And לאמו l'imo tells me only טומאת מת is the
problem, טומאת טומאת מת.
Okay. Why do we already assume it?
Because על כל נפשות מת al kol nafshot meit is about corpses?
Yeah. Yeah, but then לאביו ולאמו l'aviv ul'imo doesn't say specifically separate
phrase.
Oh, that's what
you would think that that would be in addition to this because
because they were separated.
This says don't become טמא to to corpse טומאה. tumah Then it
says don't become טמא to your mother and father. Maybe I can't
become טמא to any טומאה that my mother and father has.
Okay. So לאמו l'imo tells you the same way לאמו l'imo by
נזיר is במותם, bemotam, לאמו l'imo here is also only corpse טומאה.
Okay, so basically whether based on קל וחומר, kal vachomer, whether based
on the fact that we start by saying that a normal כהן
is already a כהן הדיוט, kohen hedyot, so we know he can't
become טמא to non-relatives, to רחוקים, rechokim, על כל נפשות מת al
kol nafshot meit must mean relatives. If על כל נפשות מת al
kol nafshot meit means relatives, לאביו ולאמו l'aviv ul'imo are both extra.
So לאביו l'aviv comes to say yes you can become טמא to
a מת מצווה meit mitzvah and לאמו l'imo tells me yes you
can become טמא if it's not a טומאת מת.
But that גזירה שוה gezeira shava also then comes to include אביו.
aviv. Like it says you would think that maybe it would be
that you can
be טמא for any kind of טומאה from your mother and father.
From your mother and father could have just said just the mother
not also the father.
What are you saying? Why do I need אביו? aviv? Yeah. אביו
aviv tells me that that you're allowed to become.
I know what it tells you but but the last step, right?
Where it says you you might have thought that it would be
for all kinds of טומאה but it's not. It's only for טומאת
מת for the mother.
Oh yeah, yeah, not just the mother. Yeah, yeah, now the mother
doesn't mean mother, right? Now once once this means all relatives, these
are just magic extra words that tell me other הלכות halachot that
are not specific about mother and father, okay? So then these are
extra words and the extra words just tells me something extra. Okay,
so we'll end with that.